Guide to the English Miscellaneous Manuscripts Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
English Miscellaneous Manuscripts Collection
1362-1945
MS 753
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
8.25
An artificial collection of correspondence, financial, legal, and government documents, political memoirs, military records, literary manuscripts, and autographs relating to Great Britain, 1362-1945. An anonymous essay about Charlotte Corday, memoirs attributed to George Grenville, and writings by George Grote and Sir Henry Maine are included.
Scope and Contents
The papers in this collection have cross-reference slips in the manuscript catalog and fuller descriptions in the inventory catalog. However, these slips do not indicate where in the collection items may be found. It may be necessary for the reader to look in several containers in order to find an item. Unless the item is one of the few which this listing mentions individually, or is likely to be one of the autographs in box 15 or one of the large legal documents in folio 21 A+B, it is probably best to begin by checking under the proper date in boxes 1-9. Small legal documents will also be found here. If the item is not found, the reader should check folios 18 and 21 A+B (or box 12 if the date is 1848 or 1850). Items in these folios, as in boxes 1-9, are in chronological order and may be quickly found. It is possible, however, that an item, to which a date is assigned in the catalog, has been misfiled in the "undated" section at the end of boxes 9 and 10, folio 48, and folio 21 A+B.
This collection is no longer expanding. New acquisitions are being added instead to the English Miscellaneous Manuscripts - Numbered Series, and individually cataloged in the manuscript and union catalogs.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Radicalism; Europe; Great Britain -- Description and travel; Great Britain -- History; Great Britain -- Intellectual life; Great Britain -- Politics and government; Great Britain -- Social conditions; Great Britain -- Social life and customs; Great Britain; Canning, George, 1770-1827; Churchill, Winston, 1874-1965; Cobbett, William, 1763-1835; Corday, Charlotte, 1768-1793; Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658; Gladstone, W. E. (William Ewart), 1809-1898; Grenville, George, 1712-1770; Grote, George, 1794-1871; Le Heup, Isaac, 1685 or 1686-1747; Lytton, Edward Robert Bulwer Lytton, Earl of, 1831-1891; Madan, Falconer, 1851-1935; Maine, Henry Sumner, 1822-1888; Pym, John, 1584-1643; Townshend, Charles, 1725-1767
- Inventory, 1362-1945
  - General Papers
    - 1362-1626 (Box 1)
    - 1629-1678 (Box 2)
    - 1679-1686 (Box 3)
    - 1690-1735 (Box 4)
    - 1690-1735 (Box 4A)
    - 1736-1774 (Box 5)
    - 1776-1836 (Box 6)
    - 1836-1879 (Box 7)
    - 1880-1903 (Box 8)
    - 1904-1945 (Box 9)
    - Undated
      - A-L (Box 9)
      - L-Z (Box 10)
  - General Papers: Oversize
    - Edward IV (1442-1483): document with seal (missing, 1980 Sep), [1476?] (Box 11)
    - John Collett: letters to an uncle and a sister (photostats), 1650 (Box 12)
    - Charles Lennox Richmond, 2nd Duke of Richmond (1701-1750): letters from the Duke of Newcastle, Henry Pelham, Andrew Stone, and Sir T. Prendergast (photostats), 1739-1749 (Box 12)
    - Various, 1848, 1850 (Box 12)
    - Valentine Browne Kenmare, Earl of Kenmare (1788-1853): catalog of library, Undated (Box 13)
    - Great Britain, Patent Office: Letters patent granted to John Holt, Jr., 1832 (Box 14)
  - Autographs and Biographies of Eminent Englishmen
    - 20 biographies of famous men and women: manuscript, in volume, with engravings, [19th century] (Box 15)
    - Autographs of British statesmen, 1769-1846, undated (Box 15)
    - Engravings and autographs of royalty, 1820, undated (Box 15)
    - Album of autographs, collected by Jemima E. (Branfill) Harrison, John Branfill Harrison, and Edith Dering Harrison, 1715, 1746, 1794-1917, undated (Box 15)
  - Jones, Daniel, d.1847
    - Ms, "Business letter book..." with 5 pay orders laid in, 1838, 1839 January 8, 1840 January 4, 1841 February 18, 1841 April 21, 1842 February 2 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Ms, "Business letter book...", 1838-1844 (Box 16, Folder 2-3)
  - Jones, Elihu
    - Ms account book of the estate of John Vyse, perhaps of Eton, kept by Elihu Jones as executor. 1v., 1789-1801 (Box 16, Folder 4)
      General note
      John Jones figures prominently in the transactions.
      The pages are loose and erratically numbered.
  - Jones, John, Sr., b.1825
    - Notecard, invitation to him "...to Dine with your newly elected Members...Wendover...", 1826 June 9 (Box 16, Folder 5)
      Wendover had an election to Parliament in this year, and this may be an allusion to new members of Parliament.
      Removed from one of the account books of the Jones family of Wendover, Bucks.
  - Jones, John
    - Ms. memorandum book listing commodities to be purchased possibly for John Jones, but not in his hand, together with entries about rentals, 1828-1829 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Jones, The Reverend Mr.
    - Ms., church notebooks kept by the Rev. Mr. Jones as pastor of the Church of Christ (Congregational) in Epping, Essex, giving outline of 4 sermons and the texts of many. At the back of the volume are nine pages of inventory of personal and household legacy receipts, accounts, etc. of [John] Vyse's will, which may indicate that the inventory was for Elihu Jones's house. He was one of John Vyse's executors. (Box 16, Folder 7)
      See also: box 16, folder 4
    - Also in the same volume, 4 pages of ledger entries for rents collected in London. In the hand of Daniel Jones?, 1812-1820 (Box 16, Folder 7)
      In the letter books of William Jones, Jr., it appears that Daniel Jones settled the estate of his brother Elihu.
    - Ms. household and rental accounts, 1820-1823 (Box 16, Folder 8)
      No covers. On verso of the last sheet are drawings of two birds in color.
  - Jones, William, Jr.
    - 2 ms. copy books of letters written from Wendover and London, England to his family (mainly his father) in Brooklyn, New York, 1847 August 16-1848 May 5 (Box 16, Folder 9)
      William Jones, Jr. was in England to settle the estate of his uncle, Daniel Jones of Wendover. He spent most of his time in London, but also visited Paris.
  - Pearson, Adam & Co.
    - Bill of exchange in favor of S.M. Swift of Surinam, Dutch Guiana, drawn on Adam Pearson & Co., London, 1893 April 10 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Endorsed on verso by Swift in favor of James Stevenson of Boston. Paramaribo, Dutch Guiana., 1893 April 10 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Christie, Gabriel, 1722-1799
    - ALS to Thomas Bullock on money matters and to ask him to thank General Prevost for his help to his nephew. [4] p., 1722-1799 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - ALS to Colonel Glen at Schenectady on laying in fifteen hundred loads of wood, informing Glen that the Earl of Loudoun will pay for putting up a fence and gate, but not for splitting firewood. 1 p., address on verso, 1754 December 4 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Becker, Thomas
    - ALS conveying an obituary to an unidentified correspondent for publication "this month." London, 1 p., 1793? October 26 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Seven Years' War, 1756-1763
    - AD (contemporary copies of originals), 1761 and 1763, concerning British supply arrangements and accounts in Germany with a listing of the British bakery and infirmary wagons, horses and servants in Hameln, 1761 Oct 20, the Hessian bread wagon train in Hameln, 1761 Nov 5, and the train for the service of Duke Ferdinand, Hameln, 1761 Nov 5. In addition there are copies of King George III's appointment of a commission consisting of Thomas Pownall, Charles Wolfran Cornwall and David Cuthbert for "Inquiring and Stating the Debts for Extraordinaries in Germany," together with "Instructions" [incomplete], 1763 Sep 21. Also a copy of a letter from Thomas Whately to the Commissioners for Examining German Demands, 1763 Oct 17 transmitting a minute of His Majesty's Treasury, 1763 Jul 15 with further instructions for the commissioners. [14] p., 1761-1763 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Greg, Walter Wilson, 1875-1959
    - ALS to Mr. Troscall with corrections for the Griggs facsimile, 1880, of Midsummer Night's Dream, London, [2] p., 1935 February 6 (Box 17, Folder 4)
      Removed from Midsummer Night's Dream, Shakespeare Quarto facsimile, London, 1880.
  - Fort Montague Bank
    - DS (printed form filled in), promissory note numbered 28962 and signed by T. Hill for the governor of Fort Montague & Co. Made out to John Flag., 1807 April 5 (Box 17, Folder 5)
      Sheet. 11 x 17 cm. Inlaid and repaired.
  - Guy, Henry, 1631-1710
    - ADS, pay orders to Sir Robert Howard, auditor of the Exchequer, to issue payments at the desire of "the Lord Commissioner] of his Ma[jesty's] Treasury." All signed by Guy and endorsed on the verso., 1631-1710 (Box 17, Folder 6)
      - For payment to Phillip Burton out of "Popish" funds, 1681 February 7
      - For payment to Bevill Skelton out of funds lent by Charles Toll, 1683 February 5
      - For payment to the paymaster of the Forces and "myself for his Ma[jesty's] Secret Service" out of "Excize money", 1683 November 17
      - For payment to Lord Lucas, Phillip Burton, Ursula Elliot and "myself for his Ma[jesty's] Secret Service." Funds advanced to Mr. Guy by Sir George Downing., 1685 July 27
      - For payment to Charles Fox, paymaster of the Forces, and to Bevill Skelton in Holland for the Scotch and English regiment, 1685 September 11
      - For payment to Phillip Burton for prosecution of law suits, 1687 July 26
      - For payment to Lord Ranelagh for the Forces, 1688/9 March 13
  - Great Britain Exchequer
    - 5 ADS, pay orders to the Exchequer. (Box 17, Folder 7)
      - Order to Sir Robert Howard for annuities to Honora Harding and Dorothy Byron. Signatures by Albermarle and three others [illegible]., 1668 May 29
      - Order to Sir Robert Howard for Thomas Baker, Agent and Consul General for Tripoli in Barbary. Signed Danby., 1677 June 28
      - Order in favor of Nicholas Johnson, paymaster of the Forces, with endorsement by Nicholas Johnson., 1680 December 23
      - Order to Sir Thomas Vernon for Bevil Skelton, Ambassador Extraordinary to the Emperor of Germany, with endorsements by Hyde, Dering, Fox and one other [illegible], 1681 August 22
      - Order in favor of Emmanuel Scroop How, groom of the bed-chamber. Receipted by E.S. Howe., 1689 January 4
    - 5 ADS, receipts for payments for services. (Box 17, Folder 8)
      - Receipt for six pounds, 13 shillings, four pence to William Tey, yeoman of the Guards., 1646 September 18
      - Receipt for six pounds, 13 shillings, four pence to John Talbott, yeoman of the Guards., 1646 September 18
      - Receipt, 1646 September 21
      - Receipt for one tally from the Tally Court "contayninge ye sume of two hundred and fifty pounds levied upon the tenthes of ye clergie within ye diocese of Exeter..." Signed [in another hand]: A. Bristoll., 1678 January 3
      - Receipt for one thousand pounds from the Exchequer out of additional tonnage, signed by Thomas Dummer for John, duke of Montagu, Master of the Great Wardrobe, upon account of the twenty thousand pounds awarded him "for his services in that office...", 1719 February 19
  - [Anonymous]
    - 2 AMS, sermons on Job 2:10 and Galations 5:22:23 preached in various English towns. v.p. [each 12 p.], 1764-1802 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Fiji. H.B.M. Consul
    - Fiji and Tonga despatches to the Foreign Office. [Suva, Central Archives of Fiji and the Western Pacific High Commission, 1968], 96 leaves, 1872 July 13-1874 February 23 (Box 17, Folder 10)
      Typescript of manuscripts in the Central Archives of Fiji and the Western Pacific High Commission.
  - Fiji. Chief Secretary's Office (Ministry of Foreign Relations)
    - Outwards correspondence - general. [Suava, Central Archives of Fiji and the Western Pacific High Commission, 1968], 164 leaves, 1873 December 13-1874 October 6 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Philanthropos, pseud.
    - Ms poem in mock heroic couplets, "Answer to some elegaic reflections composed by the Hon. Princess Eugenia on the proceedings of the 26th of October 1757." n.p., [2] p. on one leaf (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Commonplace book, Circa 1815 (Box 17, Folder 13)
    [Pious meditations on the deaths of Elizabeth Smith (1777-1806), Henry Kirke White (1785-1806) and George Whitefield (1714-1770). Also included are extracts from diaries, poems, sermons, essays on morals and religion.] n.p., 20 p., torn and stained
  - H_______, C.
    - ALS to "Dear Osgood" on the death of the writer's son and expected death of his infant daughter. [Southampton, England?] 2 p. on one leaf, 1781 September 11 (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - Autograph album of poems, religious sentiments and two drawings in chalk and gold ink. Included is a motto signed by Thomas Shakespear, described on the page as "the only known descendant of the great Poet.", 1862 May 28-1868 October (Box 17, Folder 15)
    Mutilated. Several leaves cut out. One leaf with a poem "From Test-us''" by Philip James Bailey, transferred to Beinecke Rare Book. Library. v.p., 1v.
  - Mackintosh & Hunter, merchants of London (Box 17, Folder 16)
    For Ms Invoices See: box 22
  - Madan, Falconer, 1851-1935 (Box 17, Folder 17)
    Notes on historical information supplied by Edwin Hickman of the Bodleian
    1895 Jan 26, n.p.
    1 p.
  - Stockton and Darlington Railway, Aycliffe (Box 17, Folder 18)
    Legal and financial notebook
    1849, [Aycliffe, England?]
    36 pp.
    With a further 19 pp., copy of indenture between Joseph Boulcott and John Fairweather Harrison, Thomas Barnard, and William Harrison, concerning the railway
    1834, n.p.
  - Various, 1597, 1621-1888, 1934, undated (Box 18)
  - Legal Papers: Oversize
    - Thomas Dalloway: indenture transferring land and cottage to Ithiell Smart, 1669 (Box 19)
    - Great Britain. Patent Office: Letters patent granted to Edward Thomas Hughes, 1868 (Box 20)
    - Indentures, 1602-1844 (Box 21A)
    - Indentures, 1602-1844 (Box 21B)
    - Various, 1536-1882, undated (Box 21B)
  - Mackintosh & Hunter, merchants of London (Box 22)
    Ms invoices for goods shipped from London to Messrs. Mercer & Ramsay in New York. The cargoes consist of pottery, silver, cloth, wool, buttons, stays and other domestic articles. Bound in is a letter asking for payment and cautioning the buyers not to overstock.
    1759 May 2, May 26, Jun 8, London
    13 leaves, bound together